David Stam Papers
David Stam Papers
1854-2016
Stam, David.
17 linear ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, published material and memorabilia of the American librarian, scholar and author.
4125800
Biographical History
David Stam (1935- ) is an American librarian, scholar and author specializing in book history and polar exploration, whose service to the library profession spans more than fifty years.
Stam was one of seven children (brothers Paul, John, James, and Robert, and sisters Ruth and Mary). He attended Wheaton College (1951-1955) where he was for a time the editor of the college paper, the Wheaton Record, whose journalistic independence he fiercely defended. On his father's side Stam came from a tradition of missionary work and active church involvement, and following graduation he took several courses at the University of Edinburgh's Divinity School but did not earn a degree. He served a tour in the United States Navy (1956-1958) as a Journalist 2d Class, which took him to (among other places) Antarctica and thereby launched a lifelong fascination with polar exploration.
Upon leaving the Navy Stam went to work for the New York Public Library (1959-1964) as a clerical assistant, later becoming assistant editor for library publications, reference librarian, and Manuscript Cataloger. While at NYPL he earned his Master's in Library Science from Rutgers University (1962). In 1964 he accepted a position as Librarian at Marlboro College in Marlboro, Vermont (1964-1967), where he served as Librarian and taught courses in English literature and printing history. He served as Head of Technical Services and then Associate Librarian at the Newberry Library in Chicago (1967-1973), and as University Librarian for Johns Hopkins University (1973-1978), during which period he earned his PhD in History from Northwestern University. He returned to the New York Public Library as Andrew W. Mellon Director of the Research Libraries (1978-1986), and then served as University Librarian for Syracuse University (1986-1998). After his retirement he was awarded the rank of Librarian Emeritus, and continuesdto write and teach.
Stam has served on numerous boards and committees over the course of his career, including leadership roles with the Research Libraries Group (Board of Governors, 1978-1986; Board of Directors, 1992-1998), the Independent Research Libraries Association (Chairman, 1981-1986), the Associatin of Research Libraries' Preservation of Library Materials (Chairman, 1975-1985), and Syracuse University Press (Board of Directors, 1992-1998). His scholarship spanned topics as various as research library management and frostbite; his book Adventures in Polar Reading: The Book Cultures of High Latitudes (Oak Knoll, 2019) draws together his two lifelong passions.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The David Stam Papers contains biographical material, correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, subject files, and writings by Stam and others.
Biographical material includes assorted items from Stam's childhood, his c.v., a history of the Stam family, and some personal files of his father Jacob Stam.
Correspondence contains incoming correspondence from family members, friends, and colleagues. The latter includes coworkers from the Newberry Library, New York Public Library, Marlboro College, and Johns Hopkins. Also represented are professional friends and colleagues from other institutions, such as the Morgan Library, the Bodleian, the British Library, and the National Libraries of Ireland and Scotland.
Memorabilia covers most of Stam's personal life and career, including his time in the United States Navy, his numerous awards and recognitions, clippings about him and his work, events wherein he was the featured guest or honoree, and so on.
Most of the Printed material is either by or about the various institutions where Stam worked, including Johns Hopkins University, Marlboro College, the New York Public Library, and Syracuse University. These include reports, informational brochures, invitations to special events, and clippings about the institutions.
Subject files reflect Stam's personal and professional research interests, such as libraries and librarianship, preservation, and polar/arctic exploration. Included here is research material for the 2006 Grolier Club exhibit, "Books on Ice."
Writings contains a range of scholarly and professional work, beginning with Stam's academic work as an undergraduate, library school, and PhD student, including his dissertation entitled "England's Calvin: A study of the publication of John Calvin's works in Tudor England." There are articles, book reviews, books, course material from his teaching at Syracuse University, course notes taken as a student in Edinburgh and elsewhere, encyclopedia entries, letters to the editor, library evaluation reports, speeches, and miscellany. Also included here are several works (articles, lectures, etc.) on the subject of polar exploration, including case and item labels and the catalog for Stam's 2006 Grolier Club exhibit, "Books on Ice."
A small amount of Writings by others, many of which are signed and/or inscribed to Stam, concludes the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged with family first, followed by others. Writings are subdivided by type (articles, book reviews, etc.) and within that are alphabetical by title. All other material is alphabetical by type or topic.
Separated Material
Four published items were removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. To locate these items, please refer to.
International Dictionary of Library Histories, edited by David Stam (Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers, 2001, two volumes)
Grolier 2000, includes an article by Stam (Grolier Club, 2000)
Dictionary of American library biography, Second Supplement, includes an article by Stam (Libraries Unlimited, 2003)
Famous, infamous, and forgotten: Political cartoons from the collection of Anthony J. Mourek (Grolier Club, 2013)
Subject and Genre Headings
Publishing, printing and book arts; Belanger, Terry.; Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.; Gregorian, Vartan.; Ragle, Thomas B.; Stam, David.; Wallis, Victor, 1938-; Wynne, Marjorie G.; Johns Hopkins University.; Marlboro College.; New York Public Library.; Syracuse University.; Wheaton College (Ill.); Explorers -- Books and reading.; Librarians -- United States.; Library administration -- United States.; Library science -- United States.; Polar regions -- Discovery and exploration.; Research libraries -- United States.; Appointment books.; Compact discs.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Curricula.; Diaries.; DVDs.; Exhibit scripts.; Floppy disks.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Reprints.; Research notes.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Bibliographers.; Librarians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of David Stam, 2014. 2017.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Childhood, 1935-1951 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, several versions, going back to late 1960s (Box 1)
  - Stam family history (Box 1)
  - Stam, Jacob, personal files, includes copies of his will and a few pages of financial notes (Box 28)
- Correspondence
  - Family
    - "Love letters", undated (Box 1)
    - Stam, Deirdre (wife), 1975; 2005,; undated (Box 1)
    - Stam, Jacob and Deana B. (parents), 1935; 1943-1957,; 1965,; 1970-1972,; 1979,; undated (Box 1)
    - Stam, Jacob, to/from others, 1931-1937; 1940-1941,; 1954-1955,; 1958,; 1961,; 1963,; 1972 (Box 1)
    - Stam, Jim (brother), circa 1956-1962; 1975,; 1981,; 2000; vast majority undated; includes two pieces of writing by James and a few letters from his wife Liga; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Stam, John (brother), 1985; 1989-1998; includes several articles by John, some in Spanish and a few letters from his wife Doris (Box 1)
    - Stam, Paul (brother), 1943; 1972-1975,; 1978,; 1984-1985,; 1989,; undated; includes some from his wife Jane (Box 1)
    - Stam, Robert (brother), 1959-1960; 1969 (Box 1)
    - Stevens, Ruth (sister) and Steve, 1984; 1990,; 1995-1998,; 2009 (Box 1)
    - Stam family, miscellaneous, 1935; 1955,; 1985,; 1987,; undated (Box 1)
  - Albion, 1979; 1982,; 1985-1986; North American Conference on British Studies (NACBS); Stam was on the Publications Committee (Box 1)
  - Allen, Robert, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1994-1997 (Box 1)
  - American Historical Association, 1992; includes notes for a letter to the editor from Stam (Box 1)
  - Association of Research Libraries (ARL), 1973; 1998,; 2001 (Box 1)
  - A, misc (Box 2)
  - Baker, Phil, 1972; 2002 (Box 2)
  - Banks, Paul, 1974; 1978 (Box 2)
  - Barber, Nicholas, 1972; 1975,; 1977,; 1988,; 1998,; 2000,; 2004 (Box 2)
  - Baur, Siegfried, 1998; 2007 (Box 2)
  - Belanger, Terry, 2001; 2013-2014 (Box 2)
  - Berger, Tom, 1977; 1992,; 1994 (Box 2)
  - Bidwell, John, 2014 (Box 2)
  - Bodleian Library, 1970-1975; 1978,; 1998,; 2002 (Box 2)
  - British Library, 1986-1996; 2007 (Box 2)
    See also Wilson, Alex.
  - Brown University Library, 1988-1995 (Box 2)
  - Buffalo and Erie County Public Library, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - B, misc (Box 2)
  - Commission on Preservation and Access, 1990-1994 (Box 2)
  - Council on Library Resources, 1983; 1991; related to their Task Force on Preservation (Box 2)
  - Couper, Richard, 1977-1981; 1985,; 1990,; 1993,; 1998-2006; includes background material for and draft of memorial article by Stam for American Antiquarian Society; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Crook, Arthur, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Cropp, Martin, 1973; 1986 (Box 2)
  - Curley, Arthur, 1986; 1992,; 1994,; 1998; includes obituary, "in memoriam" article by Daniel Ring (Box 2)
  - C, misc (Box 2)
  - Davisson, William Porter (Bill), 1968; 1986,; 1996,; undated (Box 2)
  - Dean, John, 1973; 1976,; 1990,; 2007 (Box 2)
  - D, misc (Box 2)
  - Edinburgh University Library, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Edwards, George, 1993; 2000,; 2003,; 2005 (Box 2)
  - Erdman, David, 1960; 1963,; 1971,; 1973,; 2001,; 2003,; 2008; includes Stam's remarks at memorial service (Box 2)
  - E, misc (Box 3)
  - Fallows, Geoffrey, 1972-1973; 1986-1989,; 1999-2007,; 2010,; undated (Box 3)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1960 (Box 3)
  - Fern, Alan, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Ferriero, David, 2007; 2009 (Box 3)
  - Floyd, Carlisle, 1997; 2005 (Box 3)
  - Fussell, Charles, 2002-2004 (Box 3)
  - F, misc (Box 3)
  - Gallup, Donald, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Gardner, Philip, 1958-1961; 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Gregorian, Vartan, 1987-1994; 2001 (Box 3)
    See also New York Public Library and Printed material: Gregorian, Vartan.
  - Gugolz, Alfred, 1956-1962; 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - G, misc (Box 3)
  - Harvard University, 1972-1977; 1987,; 1989 (Box 3)
  - Herzog August Bibliothek, 1986-1988; 1997 (Box 3)
  - Huntington Library, 1977; 1989 (Box 3)
    See also Moffett, William (Bill).
  - H, misc (Box 3)
  - Institute for Museum and Library Services (IMLS), 2003-2004; relating to Stam's service on grant evaluation committee; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - I, misc (Box 3)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1973-1978; 1988-1992,; 1998,; undated; includes photographs; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Johns Hopkins University Librarian's Reports, 1974-1976; bound volume (Box 3)
  - Johns Hopkins University Management Report, 1976; bound volume (Box 4)
  - Joyce, Bill, 1986-1998; 2014 (Box 4)
  - Kanazawa Institute of Technology, 1985-1992; mostly corporate Christmas cards (Box 4)
  - Kaufman, Annette, 1990; 1997-2006,; undated (Box 4)
  - Kjaer, Kjell-G., undated (Box 4)
  - Koizumi, Toru, 1986-1987; 1995-1996,; undated (Box 4)
  - Kossow, Richard, 2001-2006 (Box 4)
  - Krummel, D.W., 1966-1967; 1997,; 2003-2004; includes reprint of article by him, signed and inscribed to Stam (Box 4)
  - K, misc (Box 4)
  - LaBalme. Patricia, 1993; 1998-2002; most concerns Sanudo translation project; includes reprint of article by her, signed and inscribed to Stam; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Le Roy Ladurie, Emmanuel, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Lemke, Antje, 1956; 1986,; 1988,; 1991,; 1993; includes several pieces of writing by Lemke (Box 4)
  - Library of Congress, 1997; most relates to their "history of libraries" project (Box 4)
  - Linda Hall Library, 1994-1995; 2008 (Box 4)
  - Lombardi, Tarky, 1986 (Box 4)
  - London Library, 1996-1998 (Box 4)
  - Lowman, Matt, 1973; 1992; owner of Brick Row Bookshop; includes essay, "My life with rare books" (Box 4)
  - L, misc (Box 4)
  - Marlboro College, 1963-1980; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    See also Ragle, Tom; Memorabilia: "Early Voices: An Oral History of Marlboro College"; Printed material: Marlboro College
  - Meiggs, Russell, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Mills, William, Scott Polar Research Institute, undated (Box 4)
  - Milton S. Eisenhower Library, See Johns Hopkins University.
  - Moffett, William A. (Bill), 1984-1985; 1993-1994; includes remarks to ACRL (Box 5)
  - Morgan Library, See Bidwell, John.
  - Mosher, Paul H., 1985; 2003-2006,; undated (Box 5)
    See also New York Public Library.
  - M, misc (Box 5)
  - National Library of Ireland, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - National Library of Scotland, 1986-1988 (Box 5)
  - New York Public Library, 1960; 1975-1992,; 2004,; undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - New York Public Library Center for Scholars and Writers, 2004; application for fellowship (Box 5)
  - New York Society Library, 1994 (Box 5)
  - New York Times, 2005; 2009 (Box 5)
  - Newberry Library, 1970-1978; 2 folders (Box 5)
    See also Towner, Bill.
  - Northwestern University, 1964-1972; 1978 (Box 5)
  - N, misc (Box 6)
  - O, misc (Box 6)
  - Pearson, Lennart (Len), 1942; 1956-1963,; 1973,; 2002 (Box 6)
  - Phelan, Bill, 2000-2002; 2007-2011 (Box 6)
  - Phillips, Robert (Bob), 2000; 2004,; 2006 (Box 6)
  - Prochaska, Alice, 1972-1976; 1984-1987,; 1998-1999,; undated (Box 6)
  - P, misc (Box 6)
  - Quarrie, Paul, 1987; Eton College, England (Box 6)
  - Ragle, Tom, 1995; 2001,; 2006-2007 (Box 6)
    See also Marlboro College.
  - Rare Book School, See Belanger, Terry; Writings: Miscellaneous: Consultant's report on the Book Arts Press and Rare Book School
  - Resnik, Regina, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Rio de Janeiro police department, circa 1957 (Box 6)
  - R, misc (Box 6)
  - Safire, William, 2002 (Box 6)
  - St. Lawrence University, 1986; 1989,; 1992 (Box 6)
  - Seward House, 2009; includes certificate of appreciation (Box 6)
  - Shackleton, Robert, See Bodleian Library.
  - SHARP Conference, 1996-1997; includes abstract of Stam's presentation (Box 6)
  - Skeel Fund, 1963; application for funds to develop woodwind bibliography (Box 6)
  - Smith, Lacy Baldwin, See Northwestern University.
  - Sollish, George, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Stanford University Libraries, 1987-1993 (Box 6)
  - Stoppard, Tom, [2008] (Box 6)
  - Syracuse University, 1982-2009; 2013; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Syracuse University annual reports, 1986-1998; bound (Box 6)
  - Syracuse University annual reports, 1986; 1995,; 1998 (Box 7)
  - S, misc (Box 7)
  - Taylor, Paul, undated (Box 7)
  - Thieme, Paul H., 1956-1959 (Box 7)
  - Towner, Bill, 1966-1979; 1984-1989,; 1992,; 2001 (Box 7)
    See also Newberry Library.
  - Tremper, Allan, 1974-1975; undated; includes paper on Edward Gibbon (Box 7)
  - Truesdell, Clifford, 1974-1978 (Box 7)
  - T, misc (Box 7)
  - Ugawa, K., 1985-1986; 1993 (Box 7)
  - United States Department of Education, 1992; invitation to serve on grants committee (Box 7)
  - U, misc (Box 7)
  - V, misc (Box 7)
  - Wallis, Victor and Inez, 1962; 1985,; 1989,; 1994,; 1997,; 1999,; 2005,; 2011,; undated; includes a number of articles and other pieces by Victor (Box 7)
  - Wendell, Edward E., 1973; 2014 (Box 7)
  - Wheaton College, 1953-1954; 1965; includes some from Stam's time as student and editor of Wheaton Record (Box 7)
  - Whitehill, Walter Muir, 1961-1964; includes reprint of tribute to him (Box 7)
  - Williams, John A., 1997; 2001-2002; includes photocopy of libretto for opera, Vanqui (Box 7)
  - Wilson, Alex, 1986-1991; 1995,; 1998,; 2000 (Box 7)
  - Woodward, David, 1974; 1976,; 1985-1988,; 2004,; 2008-2012,; 2015; includes broadsides and other items from the "History of Cartography" project; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Wynne, Marjorie, 1998-2001; 2004 (Box 7)
  - W, misc (Box 7)
  - Yale University, 2005; "Global Record" conference (Box 7)
  - Z, misc (Box 7)
  - First name only, A-D (Box 7)
  - First name only, E-W, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Unidentified or multiple (Box 8)
- Memorabilia
  - Address lists (Box 8)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Appointment books, 1998-2003; 2005-2007; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Awards, 1956; 1962,; 1964,; 1972,; 1985-1986,; 2005,; 2012-2013,; undated; includes degrees, certificates of appreciation, academic honors, etc. (Box 8)
  - "Books on Ice" exhibit, Grolier Club, 2006; invitations, reviews, letters of congratulation, etc.; includes remarks from exhibit reception and opening (Box 8)
  - Caricatures and cartoons of Stam (Box 8)
  - Clippings about Stam, 1968; 1978,; 1981,; 1983,; 1987-1991,; 1996-1998,; 2003,; 2006,; 2012-2015,; undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Diaries, 1955-1956; Edinburgh student years (Box 9)
    See also United States Navy: Diary below.
  - "Early Voices: An Oral HIstory of Marlboro College", 2008; stam_d_001; DVD (Box 9)
  - Events
    - Stam as featured guest, 1963; 1980,; 1992-2009,; 2015,; undated; speaker, presenter, performer, honoree, etc. (Box 9)
    - Hosted by Stams, 1988; 1994-1997,; 2000-2001,; 2006,; 2015,; undated; parties, fundraisers, etc. (Box 9)
    - Memorial services, 1980; 1983,; 1988-1989,; 1992-1997,; 2000,; 2004,; 2008-2013; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Weddings, anniversaries, birth announcements, 1996; 2000,; 2010 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1994; 2001-2002,; 2006-2007,; 2013; 4 folders (Box 9)
  - New York Public Library album, 1986; presented to Stam on his departure, with farewell notes and well-wishes (Box 10)
  - Photographs (Box 10)
  - Poems, some in Spanish (Box 10)
  - Posters for Syracuse Symposium, theme "Journeys", 2003; 2 items (Oversize 1)
  - Poster, Syracuse University, 1997; aerial view, overprinted with SU mission and vision; signed and inscribed to Stam from Chancellor Kenneth Shaw (Oversize 2)
  - Postcards (Box 10)
  - "Thoughts on reaching an only 21st birthday", 11 Jul 1956; Stam's thoughts, handwritten (Box 10)
  - United States Navy
    - Deck logs, USS Wyandot, 1957-1958; photocopies, with letter from National Archives (Box 28)
    - Diary, 1957; ports of call mentioned include Spain and Greece (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 28)
  - Type specimens, 2009; three broadsides printed with specimens of two fonts, Gothic Tuscan Italian and Tusk (Oversize 2)
  - Wheaton College yearbook, The Tower, 1955 (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
- Printed material
  Types of material include pamphlets, publicity, informational brochures, catalogs, clippings (original and photocopies), and so on.
  - Balanchine, George (Box 10)
  - Gregorian, Vartan (Box 10)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Box 10)
  - Marlboro College (Box 10)
  - Marlboro College catalogs, 1963-1969; large bound volume (Box 27)
  - New York Public Library, by, 1911; 1955,; 1966,; 1978,; 1983-1989,; undated; informational brochures, special event announcements, etc.; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - New York Public Library, about, 1854; 1979-1980,; 1984-1985,; 1990,; 2012-2013; clippings (Box 11)
  - Newberry Library, 1891; 1940,; 1978-1979,; 1995 (Box 11)
  - Syracuse University, 1990-1993; 1997,; 2010 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952-2015; undated; clippings, reprints, other assorted miscellany; 3 folders (Box 11)
- Subject files
  - American Seaman's Friend Society, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Archives (Box 11)
  - Baker, Nicholson, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Bassoons (Box 12)
  - "Books on Ice" exhibit, Grolier Club
    - Funding solicitations (Box 12)
    - Item loans, pick lists, loan forms, correspondence, etc., foldered by lending institution; 17 folders (Box 12)
    - Items doubtful or rejected (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Burleigh church history (Box 12)
  - Conspectus approach (Box 13)
  - Deaccessioning, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Historiography, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Jones, Bassett (Box 13)
  - Kyd, Thomas (Box 13)
  - Lehigh University Libraries, includes report on their rare book collection by Daniel Traister; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Levine, Joseph M., 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Librarianship, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Library of Congress security, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Library history (Box 14)
  - Psychohistory, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Rare books librarianship, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Rare Books and Manuscripts Section (RBMS) (Box 14)
  - Rochberg, George (Box 14)
  - Romantics (Box 14)
  - Sassoon, Siegfried (Box 15)
  - "Special collections speech", 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Towner, Bill (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, clippings, photocopied chapters, etc. on various topics; 3 folders (Box 15)
- Writings
  - Academic work
    - Undergraduate, Wheaton College, 1951-1955 (Box 15)
    - Library school, Rutgers University, 1959-1962; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - PhD, Northwestern University, 1968 (Box 15)
    - PhD, Northwestern University, 1969-1972; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - PhD dissertation, 1978; notes and typescript draft; 5 folders (Box 16)
    - PhD dissertation, 1978; bound copy (Box 16)
    - PhD dissertation, 1978; bound annotated bibliography (Box 17)
  - Articles, material for a given article may include notes, research material, drafts, reprints, and published versions
    - British studies at the Newberry Library, 1974 (Box 17)
    - Donald G. Wing, in Grolier 2000, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Wing 10/99 Allworth, stam_d_002; files not viewed, but almost certainly connected with entry on Wing for Grolier 2000; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 17)
    - Elitism and the common cause, 1979 (Box 17)
    - Footnotes to the history of classification, 1979 (Box 17)
    - A Glutton for books: Leigh Hunt and the London Library, 1998 (Box 17)
    - Leigh Hunt and the True Sun: A list of reviews, 1974 (Box 17)
    - A Modest case against faculty selection, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Peaks of joy, valleys of despair: The history of the Syracuse University Library from 1871 to 1907, 1995 (Box 17)
    - "Prove all things: Hold fast that which is good": Deaccessioning and research libraries, 1982; revised version of speech (see below) (Box 17)
    - Think globally but act locally: Collection development and resource sharing, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Think globally but act locally: Collection development and resource sharing, 1985; in Library Lit. 15 - The Best of 1984 (Box 18)
    - Wheaton Record, miscellaneous, 1952-1953 (Box 18)
  - Book reviews
    - Miscellaneous, A-Z by author, 1963; 1980-1984,; 1988-1992,; 1998-1999,; 2001 (Box 18)
  - Books
    - International Directory of Library Histories, David Stam, ed., correspondence with contributors, notes, reviews, etc.; for the book itself, please see; 3 folders (Box 18)
    - What happened to me: My life with books, research libraries, and performing arts, 2014; blurb by Stam and reviews only; for the book itself, please see (Box 18)
  - Course materials, material relating to courses taught by Stam at Syracuse University; may include bibliographies, notes, assignments, quizzes, syllabi, etc.
    - Polar film course, 2009 (Box 18)
    - Polar heroes, 2007 (Box 18)
    - Polar heroes, 2008 (Box 18)
    - Polar journeys, 2003; taught in conjunction with Syracuse Symposium, theme "Journeys" (Box 18)
  - Course notes, notes taken by Stam when he was a student at various institutions, as well as in some cases course related material such as syllabi or reading lists